Now, in case you didn't know,
immigration is to the prosperity of the
guilded age, as Albanese gummy bears are
to my emotional well-being. Which is to
say, both realities are inextricably
intertwined, and you can't understand
one without understanding the other. So,
let's talk about immigration. If you're
ready to get them brain cows milt, let's
get to it. Okay, first things first, let
me distinguish between immigration and
migration. And I know that they sound
like the same thing, but they're not.
And it's important that you know that
they're not. So, immigration occurs when
people move from one country to another.
Migration occurs when people move within
the same country from region to region.
And during the period from 1865 to 1898,
both kinds of movements occurred in the
United States. And that prodigious
movement of people greatly expanded
America's industrial workforce. Okay, so
first let's consider a mass internal
migration that occurred during the
Guilded Age, namely the Great Migration.
And I got to be honest, as far as
migrations go, this one's pretty great.
Anyway, the Great Migration describes
the largest group of internal migrants
during this period. and it was made up
of black Americans moving from the south
to the north. And to be clear, it was
around 1890 when the migration first
started, but it continued and grew
rapidly in the early decades of the 20th
century. And there were two basic
reasons that they endured the hardship
of migration. First, they moved because
of economic hardship. Now, recall from
unit 5 that during the reconstruction
years, black Americans in the south had
made some gains thanks to the various
civil rights policies passed and
enforced by the federal government. But
after reconstruction ended, white
southerners rapidly stripped black
people of their land and kept many of
them poor through the sharecropping
system. And although there were a few
exceptions, black people in the south
had very little opportunity to achieve
self-sufficiency and economic
independence. But then to make things
worse, in the 1890s, cotton crops failed
all over the dang place and planters no
longer had sufficient funds to pay black
sharecroppers and tenant farmers. And
that sent these out of work folks to the
north to find jobs. Oh, and by the way,
if you want note guys to follow along
with this video and all my videos, check
that link in the description. Okay, the
second cause for black migration during
this period was the erosion of their
civil rights. And I've laughed my mouth
hole a lot about this in the video about
the new south, so I'll keep it short.
Basically, by the end of this period,
states across the South had enacted a
series of Jim Crow laws which
significantly marginalized black
Americans, and the Supreme Court upheld
such laws in the Pi v Ferguson decision.
Additionally, Southerners had
constructed an elaborate system of
voting that almost entirely
disenfranchised black voters. And worst
of all, white supremacist mobs were
lynching black people without fear of
reprisal from state authorities. And so,
not surprisingly, starting in the 1890s
and then about halfway through the
1900s, almost half a million black
Americans left the South, and many of
them settled in industrial cities like
New York or Chicago, where they
contributed significantly to the
expansion of the industrial workforce.
However, don't get the impression that
the North was free of racial
discrimination and segregation. No, the
North was also home to several infamous
sundown towns, which were so named
because their all-white communities
posted signs around the neighborhood
mandating that non-white people must
leave before sundown or else face
retribution. And of course, another
significant example of internal
migration during the guilded age was the
mass rural to urban migration of farmers
who sought urban industrial jobs because
they had lost their farms due to the
commercialization of agriculture. But
now let's consider the effects of
international immigration during this
period because it was immigrants who
were mainly responsible for the
expansion of the workforce in the
guilded age. Now recall that in the
first half of the 19th century there was
another significant wave of immigration
and the majority of those immigrants
came from Western Europe, specifically
Germany and Ireland. But during this
period, the immigrants showing up in the
United States came from countries in
Eastern and Southern Europe like Italy
and Poland and Russia. And then you had
other groups like Japanese and Mexican
immigrants who showed up in the United
States as well. Now, although Chinese
immigrants were banned thanks to the
Chinese Exclusion Act of 1882, and we'll
talk all about that in the next video,
Japanese immigrants were still allowed
in and they mainly settled in Hawaii and
on the western coast. And on the whole,
industrialists were just fine with this
arrangement because now that they have
been deprived of Chinese labor, Japanese
immigrants filled a lot of those jobs.
And as for Mexican immigrants, about
half a million of them came to the
United States and settled mainly in the
Southwest where they contributed labor
to the growing industrial mining and
agricultural industries. Okay, so now
let's consider the main reasons that led
to the spike in migration and
immigration during this period. And if
we had a few hours, I could give you
about a thousand reasons because there
were a lot of different groups and they
all had nuanced reasons for moving. And
I know that sounds like metric
buttloadads of fun, but I will
discipline myself and just give you
three of the main reasons for movement
in the Gilded Age. First, people
immigrated in order to escape economic
hardship. For example, during the second
half of the 19th century, the European
population exploded at the very same
time that the growing mechanization of
agriculture left millions of rural
workers without a way to earn a living.
Therefore, once these developments
spread to Eastern and Southern Europe,
it provided a significant incentive for
many of these people to immigrate to the
United States. And that was also the
case with many of the early Japanese
immigrants. In the last quarter of the
19th century, Japan's population
increased rapidly, and that put enormous
amounts of pressure on the working class
since there weren't enough jobs to go
around. Okay. Now, the second main
reason people immigrated during this
period was to escape religious
persecution. And the best examples of
this category were the Russian and
Polish Jews who immigrated to America.
So, in the 1880s, a wave of anti-Jewish
pograms broke out in Russia. In case you
don't know, the word pogram means to
smash. And that is exactly what the
Russians attempted to do to its Jewish
population. It was caused by the spread
of misinformation that a Jew had led a
plot to assassinate Thesar. And despite
the fact that there was little to no
evidence to support this claim, Russians
already possessed a simmering
anti-semitism. And this event got that
pot to boil right over the top. And so
Russian mobs began targeting Jews and
enacting violence upon them. And for
that reason, a significant number of
Russian and Polish Jews left their homes
and migrated to the United States in
hopes of finding religious refuge. And
then the third main reason that people
immigrated during the guilded age was
because they had limited opportunities
for social mobility in their home
countries or regions. For example, not
only did the population increase make it
hard for young Japanese men to earn a
living, so too did Japan's primogenature
laws.
>> Primaga what? Primagenure. It means that
only the eldest son can legally inherit
the family's wealth and property. And so
quite a few of the Japanese immigrants
who left for America viewed it as a land
of opportunity where they might improve
their social standing in a way that they
could not at home. And by the way, the
primogenature thing was also a big
reason for immigration from Europe.
Okay. And then finally, let's talk about
two major effects of the second wave of
19th century immigration. The first
effect was an increase in urbanization,
which refers to the geographic and
population growth of cities. So, the
vast majority of the immigrants that
I've been talking about settled in
industrial cities because that's where
the jobs were located. But not only were
cities growing, their demographic
composition was also changing. You see,
during the Gilded Age, the middle and
upper classes did a little migrating of
their own, which is to say they moved
out of the cities and into a new kind of
settlement outside the city known as a
suburb. And so, with the fancy schmancy
people gone, industrial cities were
increasingly made up of the workingclass
and the urban poor. And many of them
were immigrants. And in the cities where
the separation occurred, the
working-class districts often became all
kinds of squala. Like immigrants and
other members of the working class
crowded into hastily built tenementss
which were poorly constructed and poorly
ventilated. And in addition to the
depressing condition of such living
spaces, the residents close proximity to
one another assured frequent outbreaks
of diseases like chalera and typhus and
tuberculosis. So that's nasty. But then
the second and related effect of
immigrants settling in cities was the
creation of ethnic enclaves. Now,
immigrants during this period tended to
be poorer than the immigrants who
arrived during the first half of the
19th century. Therefore, when the
various groups of immigrants arrived in
industrial cities, they tended to
cluster together in ethnic neighborhoods
where they kept their cultural
traditions alive and created bonds of
mutual support. And more to the point,
these neighborhoods created the occasion
for immigrants to support each other and
help ease the transition of new
immigrants who arrived in America
weekly. Now, I'll give you two quick
examples of these ethnic enclaves, but
just know that there were hundreds of
these neighborhoods and cities across
the country. First of all, you had
Chinatown in San Francisco. This was the
largest Chinese community in California
and was formed during the gold rush and
railroad boom before the Chinese
Exclusion Act had gone into effect. And
the Chinese immigrants who lived here
created informal organizations to help
each other find jobs and campaign
against legislation that marginalized
the Chinese. They also published
newspapers in their own language and
sponsor cultural events like parades.
And then the second example I'll give
you is Little Italy in New York City.
Now, this Italian section of Manhattan
was established during the first wave of
Italian immigration in the 1840s. But
during the 1880s, huge waves of Italian
immigrants arrived and settled in this
area. And the makeup of Little Italy in
many ways mirrored the geographical
division of Italy itself. Since
Sicilians and Genevies and Northern
Italian immigrants settled into their
own neighborhoods in New York and in
those neighborhoods, they established
Catholic churches and cooked Italian
cuisines and soon those cultural traits
spread throughout Manhattan. Okay, you
can click here to watch my other videos
from unit 6, or you can click here to
grab my video note guides, which are
going to help you get all the contents
of this course firmly crammed into your
brain folds. I'm glad you came around
and I'll catch you on the flipflop. I'm
Lorett.